An event can be extremely likely and not happen, or an event can be extremely unlikely and
still happen.
This is an idea that many people find confusing.
In today's video, we'll be discussing probability and why it's important for investors to have
a good understanding of how it works.
is the study of events and outcomes that involve an element of uncertainty. Rolling a dice,
for example, involves uncertainty, as does investing in the stock market. Rolling two
dice at the same time has an uncertain outcome, but some outcomes are more likely than others,
and the likelihood of the different outcomes can actually be quantified.
While most people do understand probability, in the real world few actually seem to believe in it.
People understand that certain outcomes are rare and that the best you can do is to make decisions
where the odds are generally in your favor. They understand that you can make a wise decision and
end up being wrong or make a badly thought out decision and still end up right because that's
just how luck and risk work. But almost nobody actually uses probability in the real world
when judging things, in particular things like other people's successes. What people instead
care about is, were you right or were you wrong? Probability is about nuance and gradation,
but in the real world, people see things as being more black and white. If you said something will
happen and it happens, you were right. If you said it will happen and it doesn't, you were wrong.
That's how people think, because it's easier to analyze outcomes than the thought process
underlying a prediction. A famous example can be drawn from the 2016 U.S. presidential election,
where American statistician Nate Silver calculated a 71% chance that Hillary Clinton would win the
election that Donald Trump went on to win. Silver had been named one of the world's 100
most influential people by Time magazine in 2009 after his election forecasting system
successfully predicted the outcomes in 49 out of the 50 states in the 2008 US presidential election In the 2012 U presidential election his forecasting system correctly predicted the winner of all 50 states and the
District of Columbia. Nonetheless, the main takeaway in 2016 was quite simply that Nate Silver was wrong.
Great examples can be drawn from the 2020 coronavirus pandemic as well.
News headlines say things like, experts predict 700,000 deaths by the end of July.
What they should say is experts have a 95% confidence that the number of deaths by the end of July will be between 550,000 and 850,000 or something like that.
It doesn't necessarily make a snappy headline, but that's actually what a prediction looks like.
With the original headline, if the number of deaths by the end of July turns out to be, say, 650,000,
people will declare the experts wrong, even though it was pretty close.
If the number turns out to be 900,000, they'll be called disastrously wrong,
even though the forecasters knew there was a reasonable chance of that occurring.
Misunderstanding probability happens a lot in investing too.
Predictions that come true bring invitations to talk on CNBC.
Predictions that don't bring mockery from those who end up being right.
Probability theory began in 17th century France,
when the two great French mathematicians Blaise Pascal and Pierre de Fermat
corresponded over problems from games of chance.
These types of problems continue to influence early researchers in establishing a mathematical theory of probability.
Today, probability theory is a well-established branch of mathematics that's applicable in every area of scholarly activity,
from physics to weather prediction to predicting the risks of new medical treatments.
Knowing the probability of getting heads when flipping a coin is 50%,
the probability of flipping heads on two coins flipped at the same time is then 50% times 50%,
or 25 The four possible outcomes are heads heads tails and tails Thus there is a one in four chance of flipping heads or or 25 That calculation of course only works when the two events are independent of each other
Looking at events like weather forecasts and questioning the likelihood of having two rainy
days in a row recognizes that such events are different to coin flips. Rain yesterday might
actually predict rain today because storms can last more than one day and of course because
weather is seasonal. Probability turns up in all areas of finance. Probability allows financial
professionals to calculate expected value. The expected value of an investment is simply the
probabilities of the various outcomes multiplied by the various payoffs in the different scenarios.
This is used everywhere from valuing a simple equity investment to pricing exotic derivatives.
The insurance industry is almost entirely built on probability calculations, and an important component of credit is the probability a loan will be repaid.
In my book, Statistics for the Trading Floor, which is linked to in the description below,
I work through all of the important probability calculations and how they can be applied to stock
market analysis. As I mentioned earlier, good ideas as measured by probability can turn out
badly and bad ideas can turn out well, at least in the short run. In probability theory, the law
of large numbers is a theorem that describes the result of performing the same experiment
a large number of times. According to the law, the average of the results obtained from a large
number of trials should be close to the expected value and will tend to become closer as more
trials are performed. While every lottery does have a winner, if a person buys thousands of
tickets that have an expected value of 70 cents, and they pay a dollar for each of these tickets,
it becomes a mathematical certainty that they will lose money. In her best-selling book,
Thinking in Bets, I'll put an Amazon link to it in the description below,
professional poker player Annie Duke explains how in the long run, the cumulative effect of being a
little bit better at decision making by taking probability into account can have a huge effect on how our lives work out Things like jobs and relocation decisions are bets Sales negotiations and contracts are bets Buying a house is a bet
All decisions are bets on the future. They shouldn't be viewed as being right or wrong
based on how they turn out. Duke explains in her book how professional poker players
try to avoid the intellectual foible of what she calls resulting, which means looking at a single
outcome as opposed to considering the broader spectrum of possibilities. When poker players win,
they must separate luck from process. If they can figure that out, they can improve their game and
their future outcomes and understand what was attributable to skill and what was attributable
to randomness. When a poker player or an investor loses after placing a smart bet, they should not
be upset. This is an outcome that has to happen once in a while. Understanding what would have
been the best move relative to the probabilities is what actually matters. Probability is central
to almost all of the formulas that are used in quantitative finance. Possibly the most basic
calculation that we do in finance involves projecting likely or probable cash flows and
then discounting them at an appropriate discount rate that takes risk into account. This is the
discounted cash flow model. Modeling stock prices over time and determining fair prices for financial
instruments is once again heavily grounded in probability theory, and this is how we price
options. The insurance industry is fairly obviously based almost entirely on probability.
So, why does probability then get ignored? Well, a lot of what goes on in the financial world
is an attempt to rid yourself of the painful reality of not knowing what's going to happen
next. Someone who tells you that there's a certain chance of recession happening doesn't do much to
get rid of that pain, and in fact they might just be adding to it.
But someone who says there is definitely going to be a recession this year offers something
to grab onto with both hands that feels like taking control of your future. When you realize
that making people feel better is more appealing than giving people useful figures, you start to
see why financial professionals often avoid using probability at all in their discussions.
But hopefully you can see here how important probability is and how important it is to
improve your way of thinking and to think in a more scientific manner and that using things like
probability and statistics should improve your investing performance and hopefully your life
outcomes in general. Anyhow, have a great day. Bye.